Hey everyone, this is Dr.
Ermin Talley, here with
session 3 in our series
on clinical cardiology.
Last lecture, we
focused on blood flow
through the coronary
arteries and how these
correspond to specific
lead locations.
Afterwards, we jumped
into the approach
of reading an AKG
from start to finish.
Now, we'll discuss
what happens when rate
and a rhythm are
disturbed in some fashion.
This is also known
as an arrhythmia.
so these are the deception
objectives for this
lecture the questions on
your upcoming exams your pre
-comps and comps will
reflect these objectives if
you can answer these in
your own words you're
probably in a good spot and
I've included in the bottom
right hand corner some
references to first aid
in case you're using it
as a supplemental tool so
before we begin these
lectures I do want to
mention are just the
beginning of your ekg
learning and it should be
supplemented by ECG Books
and Dr. Cohn's workshop,
where you'll get
more exposure and practice
into reading AKGs.
So now, before we
jump into arrhythmias,
it's important for
us to understand what
an arrhythmia is.
So in an arrhythmia,
A refers to lack of or
not, and arrhythmia refers
to rhythm, making
arrhythmia refer to a lack
of normal sinus rhythm.
A term I don't use much
what you may see in some
textbooks is dysarrhythmia,
which refers to a rhythm
that's disorganized
so it doesn't work
properly. You can think
of the word dysfunction
as an example of this.
Dysarrhythmia may
be used in a similar
fashion as arrhythmia,
but I haven't really
seen it used that
often, but both are used
as umbrella terms for
rhythm abnormalities.
Tachyarrhythmia refers
to an arrhythmia
that causes a fast
heart rate, tachycardia.
Bradycardia or
bradyrhythmia refers to an
arrhythmia that causes
a bradycardic rate.
Like I mentioned in previous
lectures, you can also
have an abnormal rhythm
with a normal rate. Some
of the pathologies that
we've discussed and will
discuss, such as atrial
fibrillation, are treated
chronically with rate
control if attempts are made
to restore the normal sinus
rhythm are unsuccessful.
In some of these
patients, they walk around
asymptomatic with a normal
rate but an abnormal rhythm.
Ultimately, why are these
potentially dangerous? Why
do we even need to care
as physicians whether or
not our patients are in
attacky or brady arrhythmias?
So this brings us back to
a little bit of physiology.
So reviewing close friend
of ours from when we were
pre-med, the cardiac output
equation, we can recall that
a potential consequence
of changing heart rate is
changing the cardiac output.
The cardiac output is equal
to the stroke volume times
heart rate. Stroke volume
is the difference between
end diastolic filling or end
of filling and end systolic
volume, end of contraction.
In these arrhythmias,
whether they're tacky or
bradyarrhythmias, stroke volume
can go up or down depending
on the circumstance to
maintain cardiac output. A good
example of this is when
you have a bradyarrhythmia.
Your stroke volume will
increase to maintain blood
supply or oxygenation. In a
pathologic state or in a state
where your body doesn't have
the capacity to maintain
a cardiac output, this is
when we run into trouble.
The arrows seen on
this slide are an
example of how
cardiac output may be
balanced from a
changing heart rate.
There are exceptions to
these arrows, but I won't
go into them because I
would just be walking
down a rabbit hole of
physiologic mechanisms and
like all of medicine, there
are always exceptions.
Here's the thing though.
In this discussion thus
far, we've only mentioned
heart rate, not heart
rhythm. Why is heart rhythm
a problem? Well, they
usually are associated
with a change in cardiac
output as they exacerbate
an abnormal rhythm.
There are other problems
related to specific
tachyrythmus that we'll
discuss later in the lecture,
but what I want you to
get out of this slide
is that there are mechanisms
in place to restore
cardiac output when heart
rate is abnormal. So,
when you sit down to perform
an EKG, you're told to
remove your clothes, expose
your chest for the precordial
leads, then once the EKG
technician presses start,
the patient is informed
to not move or talk. This
minimizes the potential of
what is known as artifact.
You may have been exposed
to artifact in your
radiology lectures when
something shows up in an
image that is a result
of some external, not
clinically significant, or
any other disruption of your
picture. But in cardiology,
artifact refers to
anything that disrupts
your cardiac monitoring.
Muscle tremors or
contractions are one of the
most common examples
of artifact for ECGs.
A wandering baseline
caused by respirations
can also look like
something is going on,
when clinically it
is insignificant.
On the screen in the
bottom right-hand
corner, you can see an
example of artifact.
Dr. Cohen can attest that
artifact is seen on a lot
of ECGs, And you as
well, during your 30-year
rotations and beyond, will
see many ECGs with artifact.
Now the trick as a
medical student is
identifying whether
what you're looking
at is an arrhythmia
or is it artifact.
One way to identify this
in the case of a loss of
signal artifact is to see
if the QRS marches on at the
same rate before and
after the reading. In this
case, you can see the QRS
complexes marching through
the artifact shown on the
rhythm strip on the screen.
Here, you can use ECG
calipers seen on the right,
though.
Here we have a question
related to Objective 1.
Again, you can pause
your screen for about 10
seconds and come back
to us when you're ready.
Now,
artifact can hide
arrhythmia, true or false.
Answer, as you correctly
stated, is true. So
while artifact is not
clinically significant
and also referred
to as noise, it can
definitely get in the way
of EKG interpretation.
If you get an EKG with
significant artifact, you
would definitely want
to repeat it as an
arrhythmia, like her premature
ventricular contraction,
can be hiding beneath
or within the artifact.
And another question
related to objective one.
Again,
pause the screen and come back
to us in about 10 seconds. So
now we have an 82-year
-old male with a past
medical history of type 2
diabetes, congestive heart
failure, and generalized
anxiety disorder,
experiencing dyspnea and
peripheral edema up to his
knees. What is the
mechanism of these findings?
Is it increased cardiac
output, decreased heart
rate, increased cardiac
output, decreased total
peripheral resistance?
is to increase cardiac
output, decrease stroke
volume, decrease cardiac
output, decrease heart
rate, decrease cardiac
output, decrease total
peripheral resistance,
decrease cardiac output,
decrease stroke volume.
Now before we dive into
this, let's look at the
question stem. This patient
is experiencing symptoms
related to heart failure,
where a low ejection fraction
means that the blood is
not sufficiently perfusing
tissues. With this in
mind, we need to remind
ourselves of the equation
for cardiac output. Cardiac
output is equal to stroke
volume times heart rate.
Either heart rate or
stroke volume has to lower
to satisfy the equation
in this situation.
So another way to think
of stroke volume is
endiastolic volume minus
end systolic volume.
So as ejection fraction
decreases, this
also means that the
stroke volume decreases.
So in this patient,
we have a decreased
cardiac output and a
decreased stroke volume,
making our last option
on our screen the
correct answer, as
you correctly stated.
So now we'll discuss
the three mechanisms of
arrhythmia as they pertain
to this lecture. So the
three mechanisms we have
here are automaticity,
triggered activity, and
re-entry. So now let's
break down these words
and try to figure out
to the best of our
ability what these mean.
So number one, automaticity.
So automaticity
refers to the property of
cardiac cells to generate
spontaneous electrical
action potentials. It's
an intrinsic ability that
cardiac cells have in
the SA node, AV node, and
that can be problematic
when they don't do this
in a normal fashion.
This refers to pacemaking
abilities, phase four of
the cardiac cells. So if
you're talking about the
SA node, which is the
usual dominant pacemaker,
normal automaticity would
refer to firing that's
appropriate for physiologic
demands at a certain time.
Abnormal automaticity
would be if a patient
is tachycardic at
rest, for example.
Normal levels of
automaticity were described
in a prior lecture,
and if you remember
60 to 100 beats per
minute, you're correct.
So an example of
automaticity abnormalities
includes inappropriate
sinus tachycardia or an
accelerated junctional
rhythm, which is when the AV
node is pacing or beating
faster than the SA node.
Hereditary
bradycardia is also a
consequence of
impaired automaticity.
So basically, anything
that impairs the intrinsic
ability of the SA node to
function and produce an action
potential can be linked to
impaired automaticity. An
external example of automaticity
is a pacemaker. So when
a person has a pacemaker
and fully dependent on it,
the pacemaker
controls the rate at
which their heart
is beating at,
acting like the SA
node, generating the
action potentials to
control the heart.
So next, we have
triggered activity.
that refers to rhythms
that have an underlying
provocation, aka triggered.
These come up under
certain conditions like
hypoxia, tissue injury,
electrolyte disturbances,
etc. And these can the
layers slow down the
repolarization process. So
the result, another
depolarization that happens.
So when these depolarizations
succeed in bringing cells
to the threshold potential
that they need to fire
another action potential,
this triggers another action
potential, and that causes
the heart muscle to contract.
This isn't normal under
normal physiology, so the
degree or lack of contraction
becomes problematic.
A good example of this is
torsades de pointe, which
comes from a prolonged QT
interval or electrolyte
disturbances or ventricular
fibrillation, which comes from
usually most commonly cardiac
ischemia. This is also
sudden onset and offset.
Feel free to refer to Dr.
Zhang's lectures on the
pathophysiology of arrhythmias.
So last but not least,
reentry. So reentry is
fundamentally different
from the other mechanisms
we'll talk about, which
is why I saved it for
number three. So unlike
automaticity and triggered
activity, where the
focal point revolves
abnormalities in the action
potential within cells,
reentry involves electrical
signals that have
left their site of origin.
So they've left the
SA node, AV node, etc.
You can think more
macroscopic if that helps
you with visualizing.
But basically, it occurs
when an impulse or electrical
signal travels back and
re-excites the site of
origin, which creates a
re-entry loop or circuit.
So let's draw this out.
So here we have the
action potential within
the atria, moving down
our AV node into our
Hisperkinji system, and
finally our ventricles.
Let me label this out
for clarification.
So our atria,
our AV node,
our hisproconcie system,
and finally our ventricles.
So as the signal moves
down, it can go either
this way or along a
different pathway here.
What I'm drawing
out right now will
refer to as the
slow pathway, and on
the opposite side,
the fast pathway.
Under normal physiologic
conditions, the slow
pathway outpaces or
outcompetes the fast pathway
so that it is more
dominant and its signal
goes down and propagates
through his Purkinje
system and finally
down through the
ventricles. This is
under normal conditions.
What can happen is
if there was some
sort of re-entry
loop, there would be
an external stimulus
that can come in
and also pre-excitate the
SA node into the AV node,
which would cause and
can cause the FAST
pathway now to outcompete
the slow pathway.
And now the signal within
the FAST pathway ends up
propagating down the his
Purkinje system and then
finally the ventricles.
This is not normal under
physiologic conditions. It
can be extremely problematic.
because the heart is going
to be at a non-physiologic
pace and you're impeding
on normal cardiac
function, which can be
problematic, like we mentioned
before, based on cardiac
output and et cetera.
An example of this
includes AVNRT, which is AV
nodal re-entry tachycardia,
which is what we have just
illustrated, or AVRT,
which stands for AV re
-entrant tachycardia. The
names are pretty important
to know because it'll
help you kind of delineate
between the two where the
reentry actually occurs.
Does it occur within the
actual AV node, which
happens in AVNRT, or does
it happen between the atria
and the ventricles and
just bypasses the AV node,
AVRT?
But anyways, these
both include a loop
of electrical
conductance, like you
mentioned, with
slight differences.
with the AVRT
mechanism involving
atria, ventricles, and
an accessory pathway,
which we'll talk
about later on.
So,
question one, take
about 10 seconds,
answer on your own,
and then join us.
But all right. So,
AVNRT mechanism of arrhythmia
can be summarized with
A, impulse travels back and re
-excites the site of
origin, re-entry.
B, generation of
spontaneous electrical
action potentials,
automaticity.
Or C, an underlying
provocation, triggered activity.
So, as you correctly
stated, the answer would
be A, right? An impulse
travels back and re
-excites the site of origin,
which is the definition
of re-entry. So,
generation of spontaneous
electrical action potentials
is automaticity, and
underlying provocation
is triggered activity.
So, AVNRT's mechanism is
re-entry, like is stated
in the name, AV nodal
re-entry tachycardia.
Same approach, again,
pause, take about
10 seconds, and then
come and join us.
All right. So this patient
shows a 12-lead ECG
with normal calibration
at a sinus rhythm
of 80 beats per minute.
The axis is displayed
to the left with normal
QRS and QT intervals.
I don't see any significant ST
elevations or T
-wave inversions.
What major ECG finding
is missing upon
this report? A, portion
of orientation. B,
an interval. C, rhythm. D,
more than one of these answers.
So as you've correctly stated,
we're missing an interval.
We're missing specifically
the PR interval. We
state the orientation. This
patient shows a 12-lead ECG
with normal calibration,
all other intervals, normal
QRS and QT intervals, and
states the rhythm as sinus.
All right, so first
we'll briefly cover sinus
bradycardia. Then
we'll touch more on AV
blocks, which is another
common bradyarrhythmia.
And again, just remember
that cardiac output
is directly correlated with
heart rate. So if heart
rate is low, then cardiac
output may also be lowered.
So sinus bradycardia
is defined as a
rate less than 60
beats per minute.
All the intervals tend
to be in normal range.
And because it's termed
sinus bradycardia,
you'll see P waves
preceding all QRS complex.
Good thing to note is that
when anything is sinus,
there's a P-wave before
every QRS complex.
So the signs and symptoms
caused by sinus bradycardia
are the same symptoms as
for low cardiac output.
So patients can complain
of lightheadedness,
dizziness, potential syncope
due to decreased perfusion
to the brain. Fatigue and
shortness of breath are
symptoms that relate to
poor perfusion to tissues.
Now, just because
the rate is under
60 and it's sinus
bradycardia doesn't
mean that it's
always pathological.
This may be an example of
normal physiologic heart
rate, especially in athletes
that train, which leads
to a lower average heart
rate. The mechanism behind
this is an increased
vagal tone, which is the
parasympathetic driver of
the cardiovascular system.
These are the people that
don't really have symptoms
because it's their normal.
You can also find sinus
bradycardia during sleep. So
a good rule of thumb is when
it's asymptomatic, it's
usually not problematic. In
terms of pathology, you
can find sinus bradycardia
as a result of sick
sinus syndrome, where
basically your sinus
node is sick, it doesn't
perform quite up to par.
So we'll discuss sick sinus
syndrome in more detail
in the next lecture.
Medications are
probably the most common
clinically relevant cause
of sinus bradycardia.
Some of the many
medications that
cause sinus brady
include beta blockers,
calcium channel
blockers, opioids,
benzodiazepines, and
barbiturates. For a
more complete list
of drugs that cause
bradycardia, you can
check out some notes.
In terms of treatment,
you'll usually
want to just reverse
the underlying cause.
If this is symptomatic
sinus bradycardia in
the emergency room
without a known cause,
your first-line
treatment is atropine. Do
you remember the
mechanism behind atropine?
Right. It's an
anticholinergic, or
more specifically,
an antimuscarinic.
Thinking back to anatomy
physiology, the heart
expresses M2 receptors,
which is why atropine works.
For an ongoing symptomatic
sinus bradycardia,
patients actually are
treated with a machine
that it induces
depolarization at a
predicted rate. This is
what is known as pacing.
In a myosurgical procedure,
the pace leads are
inserted into the
heart with the pulse
generator connected to them
directly under the skin.
You can see a picture
of an actual pacemaker
under the skin in the
bottom right corner.
We'll talk about other
causes of bradyarrhythmias
such as AV blocks in the
next few and final lecture.
So now we'll jump into
the tachyarrhythmias.
Here we've listed
some symptoms of
tachyarrhythmias and
again, just for review,
a tachyarrhythmias is one
that's associated with
a heart rate of greater
than 100 beats per minute.
As you can tell, the
symptoms between brady
and tachyarrhythmias
don't really change,
So that's why it's
important to look
at the heart rate as
well as ECG patterns.
So now I'll expose you to this
algorithm for arrhythmias.
Although you may not
need to know right now at
this moment, it'll be very
important for your clinical
rotations and when
you do your ACLS, your
advanced cardiac life support
training at the beginning
of third year when
preparing for rotations.
This is a lot, but I
just want you to start
grouping these arrhythmias
in your head in some fashion.
No need to spend a
million hours on the slide
getting every detail
down. So, tachyarrhythmia
with a pulse, need to
look at the QRS duration.
Is it narrow or is
it wide? So, if it's
a narrow QRS, if it's
a regular rhythm,
you're thinking
sinus tachycardia,
AVNRT, AVRT,
atrial tachycardia, atrial
flutter, and a
junctional rhythm.
If it's irregular, you're
thinking more so AFib,
atrial flutter with
variable AV conduction,
and multifocal
atrial tachycardia.
Now on the flip side,
with a wide QRS,
so regular rhythm,
you're thinking
ventricular tigrocardia
or SVT with aberrancy.
And irregular rhythm,
ventricular tigrocardia,
which is more polymorphic
and like Torsas DuPont.
I did kind of narrow it
also on the side here. I did
include a little bit of
information just so you
can keep in mind where the
arrhythmia would be generating
from. So if you were to
look at a rhythm strip
or an EKG and you see a
narrow QRS complex, you're
thinking the arrhythmias
originating from above the
ventricles, so either the
atria or the SAAV node.
Now, if you encounter a
wide QRS complex, you're
thinking the arrhythmia
originating in the ventricles.
Those two points I would
definitely commit to memory.
It'll help you
not just for ACLS.
It'll also help you
in general when you're
reading EKGs and you're
trying to deduce what
arrhythmia is occurring
and where it's occurring.
and it also will help you
then guide management.
So now let's dive a
little bit into these
tachyarrhythmias.
We'll start first with
the narrow QRS regular
tachyarrhythmias,
which as a reminder would
be originating above the
ventricle since the QRS is
normal in these pathologies.
So the issues in the
ventricles, it's above since QRS
complex itself represents
ventricular depolarization.
so these tachyarrhythmias
with a narrow QRS complex
have a name they can be
bunched up into a group
called supraventricular
tachycardias it's not a specific
condition it just refers
to any tachyarrhythmia
that's supra or above the
ventricles meaning that
it comes from the atria
in some location it's not
the exactly the most specific
way to define a rhythm
so bringing this up as a
way of exposing you to this
terminology. No need to
overthink this slide if
you understand what
supraventricular means. Some
examples of SVT, which is
short for supraventricular,
include atrial fibrillation,
atrial flutter, AVNRT, AVRT,
multifocal atrial
tachycardia, etc.
Since none of these rhythms
originate from below the atria.
So sinus tachycardia, we
talk about this and we
spoke about this in previous
lectures. This is when
basically the SA note
is pushed past 100 beats
per minute. You'll see
P waves preceding every
QRS complex since, as the
name states, it's sinus.
And this usually has
some underlying cause,
be it from pain,
exercise, or stress.
There are some underlying
pathologies that
can also cause and
present with sinus
psychocardia, such as
dehydration, PE, or anemia.
Interesting enough,
in patients with
PE, some of them
usually, the first
clinical sign of it
is sinus tachycardia.
Now, the treatment for
this condition, considering
it has a variety of
potential causes, is to
identify and basically treat
whatever is causing it.
now another cause of
supraventricular tachycardia is
what is known as premature
atrial contractions so if
we break it down we can
see that this is defined as
contraction of the atria that
occurs before it's supposed
to from the sa node in other
words impulses originate
in the atria outside the
sa node this results in
an abnormal p-wave morphology
or shape because the origin
is from an ectopic or
external pacemaker, not the
same as our usual depolarization.
This can be seen as
a weird shape P waves that
arrive earlier than expected,
regular P wave, not
depolarizing the ventricles.
Occasionally, PACs are normal
in a non-diseased heart.
They're more frequent in
CHF, myocardial ischemia,
and COPD patients. Many
patients describe this as the
heart skipping a beat. There
isn't necessarily a treatment
for this. Usually we treat
the underlying cause.
So now if we take
a look at the first
picture, we can see a
normal distance between
P waves and QRS
complexes found here.
So this QRS complex,
this QRS complex,
and this QRS complex.
The P waves also have a similar
morphology to one another.
However, if we were
to look back At the
second QRS complex we
see here, this P wave
has a different
morphology when compared
to the other two,
excuse me, other three.
And it also kind of
overlies the T wave, which
gives us a hint that
this is likely an
ectopic beat that isn't
sinus, but a premature
beat, a.k.a. a premature
atrial contraction.
Similarly,
in the bottom photo,
we can see our normal P
wave and then we see
some T waves that look
a little odd. This
is because the P wave
prematurely is excited
from an ectopic pacemaker.
Also something to
notice is that the
interval between the
last sinus beat and the
ectopic beat is shorter,
hence premature.
I think it's easily
illustrated on the top picture.
So the distance
between these two QRS
complexes is about
two and a half boxes,
a.k.a. premature.
While we compare QRS complexes
with normal P
-weight morphologies,
they have a pretty
consistent space in between
them of about three
and a half big boxes.
So conduction to
the heart is usually
normal, but the PR
interval might be
different during
each beat as well.
So next, let's talk
a little bit about
another supraventricular
tachycardia,
and that's focal
atrial tachycardia.
Basically, this is when
a regular atrial rhythm
isn't coming from the SA
node. In this case, the
atrial rate is greater
than 100 beats per minute.
The most common ectopic
pacemaker is in
the left atrium.
The rhythm itself is
regular, but the P-wave
directions will be abnormal
due to different vectors.
This is referred to as
an unusual P-wave axis.
So the P waves, due to
their high rate, can
usually be squished
together within T waves.
In the top right-hand
corner, you can see how the
P waves are hidden within
the T waves. This is a
classic example of a
supraventricular tachycardia.
So signs and symptoms,
though, of a focal atrial
tachycardia could be asymptomatic,
can have palpitation,
shortness of breath,
lightheadedness, syncope.
usually any arrhythmia
can cause any variety of
these symptoms so it's
not specific to this
arrhythmia itself and
adenosine can usually be
used to reveal any
underlying atrial activity so
next avnrt which is
something we spoke about
previously stands for av
nodal reentrant tachycardia
and it's the most common
type of paroxysmal
supraventricular tachycardia
so if you have an ongoing
circuit, then the way we
combat this is by either
slowing or blocking
conduction within the AV node.
We can accomplish this
with physical maneuvers,
pharmacologic options, or
blasphemy of the pathway
that allows this loop to
go on over and over again.
P-ways may be retrograde,
meaning they'll
possibly be found
after the QRS complex.
Another option is that they may
be buried within
the QRS complex.
one way to slow down the
heart rate is with vagal
maneuvers such as carotid
sinus massage or basal vagal
maneuvers when you tell your
patients to bear down like
they are pushing while
constipated for example if
they're stable and symptomatic
you can try the drug
adenosine I usually think of
adenosine as the opposite of
caffeine it's an adenosine
receptor antagonist caffeine
makes you get up and go out
of your den while adenosine
makes you want to chill
in a den adenosine is a
pretty interesting drug as
patients feel an impending
sense of doom as their heart
rate very quickly drops,
sometimes seizing
for five seconds and
returning to a normal range.
For further discussion
on adenosine, feel
free to reach out.
It's a cool thing
to see in a patient,
but not so much
for the patient.
Now, let's say adenosine
doesn't work and the
patient becomes
unstable. The next option
would be cardioversion,
specifically direct
current cardioversion
or shocking the heart.
So before I lose you all in
this picture, I just want
to let you guys know again,
this represents AVNRT. This
is very similar to what we
had discussed previously.
So before we discuss again,
the pathophysiology for
review, let's discuss the
requirements for re-entry.
So there are three things.
You need two pathways to be
present within the AV node.
As we mentioned, the slow
and the fast pathways,
different speeds of conduction.
So slow speed of conduction
versus fast speed of
conduction, and unidirectional
block, meaning one
pathway is blocking the other.
These three things allow
a circuit to be maintained.
This is shown on the left
in what meets the requirements
for potential AVNRT.
The circuit usually involves
two anatomically pathways
within the AV node, again
the fast and slow pathway.
So the fast pathway
conducts rapidly and has a
relatively long refractory
period, meaning they need time
to depolarize again. The
second pathway conducts
relatively slowly and has a
shorter refractory period,
meaning they're able to
depolarize again quickly.
You can think of this
circle as the myocytes
that may depolarize
and electrical signals
are trying to reach
all the cardiac tissue.
It doesn't matter which
pathway gets to the myocardial
cell first, as long as a
coordinated depolarization
occurs. This will lead
to a normal rhythm,
and then after the AV node,
it goes forward through
the Hisperkinje system,
and finally ventricles.
Even though this may look
like something scary or not
too common, slightly less
than half of the population
have this as their normal
physiology in their AV node.
So again, the picture on
the left shows what normally
happens in the AV node,
The balance of the fast
pathway with a long
refractory versus the slow
pathway with a shorter
refractory is kept in check.
How can we disrupt this
system? Try and think
of what happens when
premature atrial contraction
comes along. The
picture on the right
shows how the classic form
with AVNRT is initiated
by a PAC, or premature
atrial contraction.
So let's talk this through
because it could be a little
conceptually challenging,
and the last thing I want
you to do is get frustrated
and leave the lecture.
So if we send a premature
atrial contraction toward
the AV node, the fast
pathway will still be in its
refractory period. Therefore,
its anti-grade, aka forward,
conduction down the fast
pathway is blocked. The
next depolarization that
the fast pathway receives
actually comes from the
slow pathway, looping around
in a retrograde fashion.
The slow pathway has a short
has a short refractory
period, meaning that it
can depolarize again
with a premature atrial
contraction. This leads to
a cycle in which the slow
pathway will re-excite
itself, backtracking from
the fast pathway. The
premature beat conducts via
the slow pathway through
the final pathway to
the normal bundle ****. As
a result, the PR interval
of the premature beat
will be longer than those
of normal beats conducted
through the pathway.
And a good tad bit to also
keep in mind is the AV
node is usually a site where
the electrical propagation
from the SA node down
to his Purkinje system
is paused briefly, which
is represented by the PR
interval. So it's not hard
to imagine that the PR
interval of the premature
beat will be longer than
the normal beats since
there is additional delay.
I would definitely
suggest listening
to this again or
looking at another
resource for a
different explanation.
These types of difficult
and these types of difficult
concepts, I'd probably
recommend drawing out a picture
explaining this to your
friend in your own words.
You can also always email
me to discuss this further.
One of the first or
major findings of an EKG
is a retrograde P wave
which can be seen in the
bottom right-hand
corner. This shows the
depolarization of the atria
after the QRS complex.
The rate is usually 150
to 250 beats per minute,
while the rhythm is regular.
P-waves may be retrograde,
seen in the bottom, or
buried, seen in the top.
Now, not to confuse you,
but there is another
condition called AVRT,
AV reentrant tachycardia.
You can think of AVNRT
as a micro version
of AVRT. So again,
in AVNRT, we see the
small and the fast pathway
within the AV node.
While with AVRT, we are
talking more globally about
how we can provide the AV
node with another pathway
towards excitation. This is
known as an accessory pathway.
It involves the atria,
ventricula, and ventricula.
An accessory pathway
causes an abnormal
conduction between the
atria ventricles. So in
this pathology, we can
see a retroactive P
-wave just like in an AVNRT
because the accessory
pathway can also
depolarize the atria.
Just like in AVNRT, if
sufficient differences in
conduction timing and
refractoriness exist between the
normal and accessory
pathway, our premature atrial
junctional, which means between
the atria and ventricle,
or ventricular depolarization
can cause re-entry.
Major clinical
correlate here is with a
condition called Wolf
-Parkinson-White syndrome.
This is probably one of the
more super high yields of AVRT.
So whenever you think of
AVRT, you should think of WPW.
I also put acute confused
wolf on the slide
to think about when
you're confused on exams.
and again treatment is
similar to AVNRT it can
be treated acutely by
shocking and although
adenosine may worsen
symptoms and again the long
-term treatment similar
to AVNRT is ablation
so here's a picture of
a regular excitation to
the AV node what we
don't want in the case of
AVRT is an accessory
pathway that creates a loop.
So in AVRT, again, it
is super pentricular.
The QRS can be either narrow,
what's called orthodromic,
or prolonged antidromic,
depending on the pathways.
I wouldn't get too much
into the specifics of
this. This is pretty beyond
the medical student level,
but it's interesting to
know and may come in handy.
Antidromic basically
means when the electricity
goes down the bundle of
Kent, then up the AV node.
Orthodromic is when it
goes down the AV node, then
back up the bundle of
Kent. So in this case, we
see an orthodromic AVRT
with a narrow QRS complex.
So now we revisit our silly
confused old friend of ours.
Let's call him Park.
He's your new pet for
the remainder of this
lecture, Wolf Park.
Anyways, back to the learning.
So Wolff-Parkinson-White
syndrome is, as stated before,
the most clinically relevant
example of AVRT. The
accessory pathway, or AV bypass
track in WPW, is referred
to as the bundle of Kent,
which of course is the
middle name of Wolff-Park
over here, Wolff-Park-Kent.
The picture in the
bottom right corner
shows the mechanism
of orthodromic AVRT
in the presence of
the bundle of Kent.
An ECG from a patient with
this AVNRT will lack the
WPW pattern since the excitation
of the ventricle occurs
through the AV node. When
we're talking about pre
-excitation, the arrow should
be pointing down from the
atria to the ventricles
through an accessory pathway.
If we know that the
bundle of Kent causes
pre-excitation of the
ventricles, we're likely
to see an early
swooping on the QRS
complex. This is what's
known as a delta wave.
The criteria for Wolf
-Parkinson's weight
is a PR interval of
less than 0.12 seconds,
a wide and QRS
complex, and a delta
wave that can be
seen in some leads.
Let me be clear, by
the way, it is only
a syndrome when a
patient is symptomatic.
If asymptomatic, and you
happen to find this on
a random patient's EKG,
they have a WPW pattern.
If symptomatic, you want
to treat in a stepwise
manner. You always start
with vagal maneuvers
if stable, then shift to
more invasive measures
like IV procanamide,
which is a class 1
antiarrhythmic, or
cardioversion if a patient's
unstable. You do want to
avoid AV nodal suppressing
medications like beta
blockers, rapamil, etc.
Because if we think
about the normal
pathophysiology of
WPW, if we block the AV
node, this would
increase the risk of
unrestricted firing from
the accessory pathway.
The definitive
treatment for this
condition is catheter
ablation of the
accessory tract,
the bundle of Kent.
Dr. Cohen has done many of
these ablations
on WPW patients.
So, if we know that the
bundle of Kent causes
pre-excitation of the
ventricles, we're likely
to see an early swooping
up on the QRS complex.
This is what's known
as a delta wave.
So the criteria for Wolf
-Parkinson-White, or WPW,
is a PR interval of
less than 0.12 seconds
with a widening QRS complexes
and delta waves seen
in some leads. So let
me be clear, by the way,
it is only a syndrome
when a patient is
symptomatic. If the
patient's asymptomatic,
and you happen to
find this on a random
patient's EKG, they
have a WPW pattern.
If symptomatic, treatment
is in a stepwise manner.
You'll always start
with a vagal maneuver if
stable, then shift to more
invasive measures like
IV brocanamide, which is
a class 1 antiarrhythmic,
or cardioversion if
the patient's unstable.
I do want to point this out,
and it's super high yield.
You definitely want to
avoid AV nodal suppressing
medications like beta blockers
and verapamil, because
blocking the AV node increases
the risk of unrestricted
firing from the accessory
pathway. which kind of makes
sense if we think back to
the pathophysiology of WPW.
But ultimately, the
definitive treatment is
catheter ablation of
the accessory pathway.
So here's a classic
look of delta
waves with a
shortened PR interval.
So we have our P
wave right here.
Now our PR interval is very
shortened, if you
can't tell. So
here's a classic look of delta
waves with a
shortened PR interval.
The delta wave refers
to this upstroke, which
shortens the PR interval.
So the PR interval
that would have been
present here is now
raised and embedded
within the delta wave.
So next, let's talk
about each category
and condition in detail
from the narrow QRS
irregular tachyarrhythmias.
arrhythmias.
So the first and probably
most common arrhythmia
that you'll be exposed to
is atrial fibrillation.
So a good way to
think about it,
fibrillation, is
quivering of muscles.
Basically when the atria
has millions of little
tugs and contractions
by the myocytes. As you
could imagine, the atria
do a pretty terrible job
of contracting and pushing
blood into the ventricles
when there isn't a
coordinated contraction.
The most common location
causing this electrical
impulse is the left atrium
near the pulmonary veins.
Atrial fibrillation
is an extremely
common condition, and
it's something you'll
definitely see on
clinical rotations.
If you're going to take
anything from this slide,
atrial fibrillation is an
irregularly irregular rhythm.
You will not see any P
waves, just squiggly lines
before random QRS pops
up, which are known as
fibrillatory waves. And for
this reason, if you don't
have any P waves, we cannot
calculate PR intervals.
AFib is classified based
on the number of episodes,
the length of episodes, and
whether it is self-terminating
or not. There are lots of
causes of AFib, but one
of the ones you don't want
to miss is hyperthyroidism.
You treat the hyperthyroidism,
the AFib goes away.
Here are two examples of
AFib. Notice the QRS complexes
are not equally spaced
and it is not unequally
spaced regularly, hence it
is irregularly irregular.
In other words, there's
no pattern to the
irregularity. So this may be
a little bit easier to show
than to put in words. So
if we were to just look at
the bottom rhythm strip
here, if we looked at first
in front of every QRS
complex, we see these little
squiggly lines. These are
our fibrillatory waves.
There are no P waves
that we can see.
next what we mean by
irregularly irregular is
that the distance
between the QRS complexes
is not the same between
them so between the
first two QRS complexes we
have a distance of about
two big boxes between
the second and the third
QRS complexes we have
a distance of about one
and a half big boxes.
And the third, we have
a distance between the
third and fourth, about
a box, one big box, and maybe
one and a half small boxes.
After the fourth big
box, if we compare the
distance between the
fourth and the fifth,
we have about two
big boxes in spacing.
So as you can tell, the spacing
that we counted along the way
we're all different so the
distance between each QRS
complex is irregular and
that irregularity that we
counted is also regular
first distance here that we
mentioned between the
first and the second QRS
complex was about two second
and third was about one and
a half third and fourth
about one big box and one
small box and finally between
the fourth and the fifth
QRS complex is about two
big boxes spaced apart.
So atrial fibrillation is
an issue because it is a
tachyarrhythmia, but
there's an additional issue.
As a general principle of
pathology, any location
in the vasculature that
causes turbulent and abnormal
blood flow predisposes
to thrombus formation.
It is mainly the lack
of atrial contraction
and hence the lack
of movement of blood,
especially in the
left atrial appendage,
that is thrombogenic. In
the atria, AFib causes
this, and it is one of the
reasons why studies have
mentioned that AFib is a
major contributor to stroke,
basically saying that
about 1 in 7 strokes are
related to AFib, which is
part of the workup when a
patient comes into the
hospital having had a stroke.
Rate control is
equally beneficial
to the patient as
rhythm control.
What this means is that
drugs that control rate, like
beta blockers, calcium
channel blockers, digoxin, or
drugs that control rhythm,
like class 3 antiarrhythmics,
can be used for control
of atrial fibrillation.
I will, however, say
that rate control
is more so used in
the clinical setting.
Rate rhythm control
does have some utility,
although rate control
is usually a first
-line option that we
first try to address.
We do need to
remember, however, that
anticoagulation is
needed, which is why
you'll see patients
with AFib on warfarin,
an oxaparin, apixaban,
or a dabigatram. I'm
not going to have the
time to do this, but
try to recall the mechanism
of action and side
effect of all these
drugs, considering how
vast the pharmacology
is just on this slide.
In the case of an emergent
symptomatic onset case of
AFib, we can always go to
electrical cardioversion,
although the ultimate
treatment is ablation to
separate the impulse
coming from the pulmonary
veins and should be easy
to understand why the name
of the ablation or the
procedure is called
pulmonary vein isolation
because we're ablating where
the impulse is coming
from the pulmonary vein.
So here's a picture of a
catheter ablation therapy
for atrial fibrillation.
The catheters advance into
the right atrium through
the intra-atrial septum and
into the left atrium.
burst of energy could be
electrical and cryoablation
are two more common methods
that create an electrical
firewall or scar within
tissue the site where the
atrial fibrillation originates
where the pulmonary vein
joins the left atrium
is electrically isolated
from the rest of the heart
now you may be asking
does everyone with atrial
fibrillation need to be
anticoagulated well clinically
there's a score that could
be assigned to patients and
a certain score denotes
which category you fall into.
This is referred to
as a CHADS-VASC score.
Now, the CHADS-VASC score
is used to stratify a
patient's need for anticoagulation
if the cause of the
atrial fibrillation or atrial
flutter is non-valvulated.
This is an important
distinction to make because
if the cause of atrial
fibrillation or flutter is
valve-related, they
automatically get anticoagulated.
If the cause is not valvular,
then find out the score.
So to help you remember
Chad's mask, I attached
a picture of Chadwick
Boseman, the actor who
played the superhero Black
Panther in 2018, and
Jackie Robinson in 2013.
Didn't have AFib,
but he was a prolific
actor who left a
big impact on the
world, so I'm happy
to include him here.
Now, the higher your
score on the Chad's mask
scale, the more prone
you are to developing a
stroke. Remember, atria
are fibrillating and
there is not the usual
atrial contraction. Due
to this, blood pools
in the atria where this
lack of movement can be
predisposed to clots.
We anticoagulate based
on the CHAZ-VAS score.
Next,
atrial flutter is
another type of
supraventricular
ticharrhythmia and contrasting
to AFib, it's
regularly irregular.
Atrial fibrillation is
caused by a reentrant circuit
in the right atrium that
circles around and through
the cavo tricuspid is
smith, which is a high yield
location to know. The most
common atrial to ventricular
contraction ratio is 2 to
1, meaning that the atria
contracts twice for every
one ventricular contraction.
Meaning that on an
EKG, you'd likely see
two P waves before a
conducted QRS complex.
For those that have not
picked up on it yet, there's
a butterfly also because
butterflies flutter.
Here is the anatomical
reentrant circuit
of atrial flutter,
where the circuit does
not go through the AV
node. Remember, the
circuit involves the
cavotricuspid isthmus.
So now, talking a little
bit more about the ECG
findings, we note that this is
a narrow complex tachycardia,
tachyarrhythmia. It can
be regular or regularly
irregular, and the main
EKG findings that you can
see with a flutter is a
sawtooth pattern or flutter
waves. You can think of
a saw how rigid it is. If
you've never handled a
saw, I suggest you look one
up and work on your handy
and house working skills.
With AFLUTR, we typically
treat it very similar to
atrial fibrillation. So
the mainstay therapy,
emergently, is cardioversion
with definitive treatment
being ablation. In this
case, we're ablating the
cavil tricuspid isthmus as
opposed to the pulmonary
vein in AFib. An easy
way to remember the
location that we're ablating
is the location of where
their fibrillation so
the mainstay of emergent
therapy is cardioversion
if unstable with
definitive treatment being
ablation in the cavil
tricuspid isthmus now where
is the cavil tricuspid
isthmus the location well
the name kind of gives
it away cavo, inferior
vena cava, tricuspid,
tricuspid valve is between
the two structures.
So next up is multifocal
atrial tachycardia aka
mat. Now with the name
you can deduce what it
means. We have multifocal
which means many origins,
atrial which is
supraventricular and tachycardia
causing a fast heart rate.
The rhythm in this case
is irregular due to the
three different P waves.
These different P
waves are also gone.
Now, the defining
feature of multifocal
atrial tachycardia is
that we need to see
at least three
different P wave shapes,
right? Again, multi, three,
so three different P
waves. The treatment
for multifocal atrial
tachycardia or mat is
rapamil or to treat
the underlying cause.
These arrows show three
different P-wave morphologies.
As you can see here, we
have one P-wave morphology,
two,
three,
so on and so forth, four,
etc.
This rhythm can be very
difficult sometimes to
distinguish from AFib, but
the way we do this is by
identifying distinct P
waves. We've identified
at least three, which
makes us think multifocal
atrial tachycardia. Whereas
in AFib, we wouldn't
see any P waves, we'd see
only fibrillatory waves.
Now, let's talk about some
tachyarrhythmias
with a wide QRS.
So first up, we have
what are called premature
ventricular contractions,
also known as PBCs.
They're kind of similar to
PACs or premature atrial
contractions, but these
ectopic beaks come
from below the bundle of
his in the ventricles.
Now, reminder, remember,
the QRS complex
represents ventricular
depolarization.
So, all of these
arrhythmias that will
originate and affect
the ventricles
would have an effect
on the QRS complex.
So, you aren't surprised
that PVCs, in this
case, have a wide or
prolonged QRS interval,
as you can see in the
top right-hand corner.
This is a fun little
quiz question. if you're
ever out to a party
with your med school
friends what is the
most common cause of pvc
lack of sleep anyways there
are a number of causes of
pvcs and you may even be
experiencing one while listening
to this lecture probably
due to lack of sleep or
some boredom I won't take it
personally but it's okay you
only need to treat pvcs if
they're symptomatic frequent
or organized into what is
known as couplets, bigeminy,
or trigeminy, meaning two
or three in a row, etc.
For more details about
couplets, bigeminy, and the
likes of, you can look at
some notes that we have
in the handout for
this lecture. It
may not be tested on
this, but it could
be helpful in
clinical rotations.
And again, definitive treatment
in extreme cases is ablation.
Now, the worst that
frequent PVCs can do is
inducing idiopathic
ventricular tachycardia.
We'll discuss this
condition on the next slide.
So speaking of ventricular
tachycardia, here we
see this dangerous
arrhythmia that puts you very
close to death. This is
a reentering arrhythmia
brought on by an
underlying cardiomyopathy,
for example. This wide
complex tachyarrhythmia
is from a single ventricular
ectopic pacemaker.
Hence, we call it a monomorphic
ventricular tachycardia.
On exams, if you see
ventricular tachycardia,
you should assume
that you're talking
about monomorphic.
So now, what makes
this monomorphic also
in practical terms?
When we look at an ECG
and we look at
the QRS complexes,
they look very
similar to each other.
This looks pretty
identical to this one,
to this one, to this
one, to this one, etc.
They have pretty much
one morphology, hence
a monomorphic
ventricular psychocardia.
Now, the P-waves
are usually obscured
or not present in
the QRS complex.
Usually patients
also with ventricular
psychocardia are
often symptomatic.
For emergent
treatment, electrical
cardioversion is the mainstay.
Pharmacological interventions
used in the ACLS protocol
you'll receive for a third
year involve alternating
between amiodarone,
lidocaine, and epinephrine.
If monomorphic ventricle
tachycardia puts
you close to death,
ventricle fibrillation
has you knocking
on heaven's door.
V-fib is a chaotic
depolarization of the ventricles
that leads to a loss of
cardiac output. The treatment
for V-fib includes immediate
defibrillation and ACS
protocol, like we mentioned
in the previous slide.
V-fib is usually caused
or result of an MI, so
if not in the setting
of an MI, it usually
requires implantation of an
implantable defibrillator,
especially if the
cause is irreversible.
Now, let's talk a bit
about Tercise de Poin.
This is a distinct
form of polymorphic
ventricular tachycardia. Now,
when we compare this to
the monomorphic ventricular
tachycardia that we just
spoke about, when we talk
about polymorphic, we're
talking about more than one
morphology. So if we
were to look at the QRS
complexes, we see different
morphologies, different shapes,
different amplitudes. So
we have polymorphism of
these complexes, hence a
polymorphic tachycardia.
So the translation in
French of torsades de
point means twisting
about the points. In
our terms, a constantly
changing QRS axis.
This is a pretty easy
ECG finding to identify
because it looks
like points on the
ECG that are separated
by a hump or humps.
The acute treatment is
usually IV magnesium as
hypomagnesemia is one of the
most common causes of torsades.
If unstable, we can also
utilize cardioversion. So
here's a 12-lead EKG
showing Torsas de Poin.
Usually this is a pretty
high-yield image to know,
especially on boards.
This is one of the ways
that they will present
Torsas de Poin on boards.
Usually they'll have
a normal sinus rhythm
preceding the chaotic
rhythm of Torsas de Poin.
In contrast,
on boards, when they
want to show you and clue
you into ventricle
fibrillation, they won't
show you the preceding
normal sinus rhythm.
They'll just show you
an EKG from beginning
to end. It'll just be
fibrillatory waves.
By this point, you
should know the drill.
Take about 10 seconds,
pause the video,
answer the question,
and then come back.
Okay. So, a patient is
unstable in ventricular
tachycardia with a pulse.
You activate the appropriate
hospital code. What needs to
get done as you are in the
room with three nurses?
A, activate ACLS protocol.
B, start chest compressions.
C, prepare and place
the pads of a defibrillator
onto the patient.
Or D, give amiodarone.
Or E, all of the above.
So, correct answer
E, all of the above.
FIFIB is a bad rhythm
to have, it's an
absolute emergency,
and everything you see
must be accomplished
as soon as possible.
Most hospitals have
some sort of co
-team that have
predetermined roles.
So again, same routine,
take about 10 second pause and
then come back
when you're ready.
So,
69-year-old female represents
to the ER with palpitations.
On EKG, you see a
sawtooth pattern,
something you recurrently
has every so often.
Her cardiologist plans for
gold standard treatment,
determining the possibility of
this occurring in the future.
What is the treatment?
A, ablation of myocytes
near the pulmonary veins.
B, ablation of myocytes
near the cavotric
cuspid isthmus. C, long
-term propranolol. D, long
-term amiodarone, or E,
ablation of myocytes
connecting the bundle
of can to the AV node.
So, as you mentioned
earlier, a sawtooth
pattern is characteristic
of what arrhythmia?
Correct.
Atrial fibrillation.
Now, the gold standard
or definitive treatment
for atrial flutter is
going to be ablation,
particularly of the
cavotricuspid isthmus region,
where the reentient circuit
is most commonly initiated.
Choice A, ablation of
myocytes near the pulmonary
veins, describes treatment
for atrial fibrillation.
Ablation of myocytes
connecting the bundle
of Kent to the AV
node, describes the
treatment for Wolf
-Margonson-White syndrome.
So here, I've included
some of the more
important information
from the lecture.
I think if you know
this information along
with some of the
pathophysics behind these
arrhythmias and how
to recognize them on
an ECG, I think you'll
be in a good place.
So that concludes
the third lecture,
Atrial Ventricular Arrhythmias.
Hope you found it
valuable to your
learning, and I
appreciate any feedback.
So feel free to email
me, my email's on
the screen, as well
as the emails of
some of the senior
members of the team.
We're around, so if
you have any questions,
don't hesitate to reach
out. Also, feel free to
join us on Mondays from
12 to 1 p.m. Eastern
Standard Time over Zoom
to review some ECGs for
more exposure with an
expert like Dr. Cohen.
And again, as always, make
sure to take some time for
yourself every day because
your mental health is an
important aspect of developing
yourself, not only as
a person, for your patients,
and also as a physician.
Best of luck to you guys.